# Abhishek Prakash

Postdoctoral Research Associate / Insight Data Science Fellow California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA

#### **CAREER HIGHLIGHTS**

Astrophysicist with expertise in analyzing large multi-dimensional datasets. Principle investigator (**P.I.**) and co-investigator of competitive peer-reviewed research proposals. Author of 30+ peer-reviewed journal articles. Reviewer for top international astrophysics journal (ApJ) and NASA NESS fellowship.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

# **Insight Data Science / Drone Base**

2019 - present

Real-time assessment of structural damage by drone

- Optimized CNN algorithm, deployable on drones, to detect structural damage in real time, saving visual inspection effort
- Implemented transfer learning with MobilenetV2 neural network using Keras/TensorFlow for damage detection
- Saved two weeks of manual work and 3-4 days of processing time per event through automated damage detection

Caltech/IPAC 2017 – present

Time series modeling and discovery of astrophysical transients

- Extracted observations from space-based optical/infrared images to construct time series of brightest objects in the universe
- Discovered 1000 new rare transient/non-stationary galaxies by employing augmented Dickey–Fuller (ADF) statistics
- Modeled long-term trends using Gaussian random walk

# Sloan Digital Sky Survey-IV/eBOSS

2012 - present

Making the largest 3-D map of the universe

- Developed and implemented new algorithms for selecting the most massive galaxies in the universe that have since been widely adopted in the field
- Improved sample efficiency by 20% while leading a team of 12 astronomers conducting analysis of the collected data
- Developed Random Forest regression algorithm for predicting distances to the galaxies based on their brightness, thereby creating the largest and most dense 3-D map of the universe
- Implemented multivariate regression techniques to model a systematic error map for the observed data

#### **EDUCATION**

Ph.D. Physics, University of Pittsburgh2011 – 2017M.S. Physics, University of Pittsburgh2011 – 2012M.Sc. Physics, University of Hyderabad2007– 2009

412 953 9160 / aprakash@caltech.edu https://github.com/abp15 linkedin.com/in/Abhi-Prakash

#### **TECH SKILLS**

#### **Machine Learning**

Scikit-Learn, TensorFlow Random Forest Regression Neural Networks/Keras Support Vector Machines

## Statistical Modeling

Multivariate Regression Receiver Operating Characteristic (ROC) Jackknife sampling Gaussian random process

### Languages and tools

Python (Numpy, Scipy, Matplotlib, Pandas, Seaborn, Astropy) Interactive Data Language Latex

# Big data tools

SQL, Jupyter notebooks, SSH, SVN, Git

#### **AWARDS**

"The Architect" award for Sloan Digital Sky Survey-IV

Arts and Sciences Graduate fellowship for **excellence** in research 2016-17, 2015-16

#### **LEADERSHIP**

Referee, ApJ Reviewer, NASA NESS Fellowship Program Co-President, Early Career Scientist group (ECS), SDSS-IV, 2014 – 2016